ILGWU. Industrial Council of Cloak, Suit, and Skirt Manufacturers. Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter, 5780/124
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Industrial Council of Cloak Suit, and Skirt Manufacturers. Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter
1939-1953.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Industrial Council of Cloak, Suit, and Skirt Manufacturers
5780/124
2 cubic feet
2 linear feet
Publications
This collection contains Current Bulletin, Weekly Market Letter, and Style and Merchandise Review, publications of the Industrial Council of Cloak, Suit, and Skirt Manufacturers.
5516875
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains Current Bulletin, Weekly Market Letter, and Style and Merchandise Review, publications of the Industrial Council of Cloak, Suit, and Skirt Manufacturers.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU records
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, July 2011
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Publications; Industrial Council of Cloak, Suit, and Skirt Manufacturers; Industrial Council of Cloak, Suit, and Skirt Manufacturers; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5516875
- Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  February 2, 1935-November 20, 1937. Incomplete. Loose issues
- Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  November 27, 1937-December 31, 1938. Bound volume.
- Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  January 7-December 30, 1939. Bound volume.
- Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  January 6-December 28, 1940. Bound volume.
- Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  January 4-December 27, 1941. Bound volume.
- Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  January 3-December 26, 1942. Bound volume.
- Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  January 2-December 24, 1943. Incomplete. Bound volume.
- Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  January 8-December 23, 1944. Incomplete. Bound volume.
- Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  January 6-December 29, 1945. Incomplete. Bound volume.
- Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  January 5-December 28, 1946. Bound volume.
- Current Bulletin and Weekly Market Letter, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  January 4-December 27, 1947. Bound volume.
- Weekly Bulletin and Style and Merchandise Review, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  January 3-December 27, 1948. Bound volume.
- Weekly Bulletin and Style and Merchandise Review, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  January 3-December 27, 1949. Bound volume.
- Weekly Bulletin and Style and Merchandise Review, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  January 3-December 26, 1950. Bound volume.
- Weekly Bulletin and Style and Merchandise Review, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  January 2-December 31, 1951. Bound volume.
- Weekly Bulletin and Style and Merchandise Review, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  January 7-December 29, 1952. Loose issues.
- Weekly Bulletin and Style and Merchandise Review, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  January 5-December 28, 1953. Loose issues.
- Weekly Bulletin and Style and Merchandise Review, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  January 4-December 27, 1954. Loose issues.
- Weekly Bulletin and Style and Merchandise Review, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  January 3-December 19, 1955. Loose issues.